[The Age of Awakening]
[觉醒年代]
[Episode Four]
[第四集]
[Qianmen Street, Beijing]
[北京前门大街]
[Li Dazhao, styled Shou Chang, editor-in-chief of the "Morning Bell"]
[李大钊 字 守常《晨钟报》主编]
Where do you live, brother?
兄弟 家在哪儿住啊
Outside Yondingmen, as a pariah.
永定门外 贱民一个
Why do you say this?
这话怎么说
Those who pull carts, wield skill in trade
拉车的 要把式的
have shaved heads, are pig butchers, coffin carriers,
剃头的 杀猪的 拾馆材的
all live over there.
都住咱们那边
Then how is getting by in life right now for you guys?
那你们现在生活过得怎么样啊
Impossible to get by. Everyone's suffering until they can't take it anymore.
没法过呀 都苦到顶了
According to the older generations' saying,
按老辈的话说
we have never gone through such sullen days.
就没过过这么整屈的日子
Didn't you say that since this President Lai has took office,
不是说这个黎大总统上任以后
he has made a lot of promises?
许了不少愿吗
President Lai!
黎大总统啊
He only cares about fighting with Duan Qirui for power,
只顾着和段祺瑞争权夺位呢
he doesn't care about the lives of the people.
哪管得了咱老百姓死活呀
Good people, I'm begging you.
好心人 我求求你们了
My child has high fever for days now.
孩子一连高热几天
I'm begging you.
我求求你们了
People are worse than animals.
人活得还不如畜生呢
Brother.
兄弟啊
Pull over for a moment.
靠边停一下
Good people, I'm begging you.
好心人 我求求你们了
I'm begging you.
求求你们了
[Zhao Shiyan, styled Qin Sheng, student at The High School Affiliated to Beijing Normal University]
[赵世炎 字 琴生 北京高等师范附中学生]
What's wrong with you?
你怎么回事啊
What's going on with this guy?
怎么回事啊这人
Go!
走
[Ge Shugui, worker at Changxindian, Beijing]
[葛树贵 北京长欣店工人]
This is my daughter-in-law!
这是我媳妇
You can't do that even if she's your daughter-in-law!
就算是你娘妇你也不能这样啊
What are you doing here?
你在这儿干什么呀
What's the point of making a fool of yourself here?
在这儿丢人现眼干什么呀
Am I ashamed? Ge Shugui!
我丢人吗 葛树贵
If... if I leave, the child will be dead.
我 我要是走孩子就是个死
We poor people are born to die.
我们穷人生下来就是等死的命
A poor man's life is not a fragile one.
穷人不是脆着的命
You can't die standing up, you know?
死也得站着不能脆着你知道吗
Go!
走
You go!
你走吧
I want you to kneel!
我要你还跪
Why are you hitting her?
你怎么还打上人了
Don't hit her!
别打人哪
I want you to kneel!
要你脆
What kind of skill is beating someone up?
打人算什么本事啊
Yeah!
是啊
Brother!
大哥
Don't fight. Don't fight.
别打了别打了
I said stop fighting!
我说你别打了
I have money.
我这儿有钱
I have money, you can have it.
我这儿有钱 你们拿去
I'll see what I can do, brother.
我想想办法 大哥
Lend me some money, will you?
借我点钱吧 行吗
Brother, save the child!
大哥 救救孩子吧
Why are you still kneeling?
你怎么还跪
Save the child!
救救孩子吧
Lend some money, brother.
借点钱吧 大哥
Lend me some money.
借我点钱吧
Sister, sister.
大姐 大姐
Save the child, save the children.
救救孩子吧 可冷可检孩子吧
Lend me some money.
借我点钱吧
Sister, sister.
大姐 大姐
Have pity on the child.
可怜可怜孩子吧
Sister-in-law, take the children with you.
大嫂 把孩子带着
I'll take you to the doctor.
我领你们去看病
Get up.
起来
Pull the cart over.
把车拉过来
Got it!
好嘞
Go now, go.
走吧 走
Mister!
先生
Mister! Thank you!
先生 谢谢您
Get up! Quickly, get up!
起来 快起来
Quickly, get up! Up!
快起来 来
Get up!
起来
Student.
同学
Which hospital is closest to here?
哪个医院离这儿最近
The French hospital.
法国医院
Come on, I'll take you there.
走 我带你们去
Alright.
好
Come, come, come.
来来来
Make way, make way.
让一下 让一下
Come on, slow down.
来 慢点啊
Be careful.
小心
Go.
走
Why are you still standing there?
还楞着干什么走啊
Come on, go!
快走呀 去啊
Go!
走啊
Aiya... I'm so angry!
哎呀 气死了
Your great kindness, mister.
先生的大恩大德
Get up.
起来
I can't repay you.
我无以为报
If you need me in the future, just ask.
以后用得上我的 您尽管说
You don't have to be so polite.
你不用那么客气
Let's get to know each other.
咱们认识一下吧
My name is Li Dazhao.
我叫李大钊
Just arrived in Beijing to run a newspaper.
刚到北京来办报纸
You are Mr. Li Shou Chang.
您就是李守常先生
I have read your book.
我读过您的书
I admire you.
我很敬佩您
Student, I admire you too.
这位同学 我也很敬佩你呀
How do I call you?
怎么称呼
My name is Zhao Shiyan.
我叫赵世炎
A student at The High School Affiliated to Beijing Normal University.
是北京高等师范附中的学生
My name is Ge Shugui, a worker from Changxingdian.
我叫葛树贵 长辛店的工人
What do you do as a worker?
您是做什么的工人
Locomotive repair.
修火车机车的 苦力
Good.
好啊
I've just arrived in Beijing and I don't know my way around.
我刚到北京 人生地不熟
Let's be friends.
咱们交个朋友吧
I can't afford that.
那我可高攀不起
Equality for all.
人人平等
There is no distinction between high and low culture.
没有什么高低贵戏之分
Sir, how can I be like you?
先生 我哪能跟您一样啊
Look at what you're saying, I can't even answer.
您看您这话说的 我都接不上了
You can't say that.
你可不能这么说
The tough talk on the street just now
刚才在大街上说的那些硬气的话
had us all in stitches.
可是把我们都给震住了
Right.
是啊
Brother Ge is a man with a backbone.
葛大哥是条汉子 有骨气
It's coming.
出来了
How's it going?
怎么样
Son.
儿子
Doctor.
大夫
Doctor, how is my son?
医生 我儿子他怎么样
Needs hospitalisation.
需要 住院
hospitalisation.
住院
It's so serious!
这么严重啊
Don't worry, it's not life-threatening.
放心 没有生命危险
You guys go ahead and check in.
你们先去办理住院手续吧
How much does it cost to get admitted to hospital.
办理住院需要多少钱
Around thirty dollars or so.
三十几块大洋左右吧
Baby will protect you.
宝宝会保护你的
Shugui.
树贵
Follow me.
跟我来
I cannot accept.
使不得
I cannot accept, Mr. Dazhao!
使不得 大钊先生
For your willingness to help us,
您愿意帮我们
we are already very grateful.
我们已经万分感谢了
How can we ask you to sell something?
怎么能还让您当东西呢
We should do it ourselves!
要当也是我们自己当啊
Do you need to go out on the street if you've got what it takes?
你要是有的当的话你用上街吗
Don't worry, these things don't get in the way of life.
放心吧 这些东西又不碍着生活
Come.
来
Short sleeves with missing lapels, few buttons and no buttons,
缺襟短袖 少纽无扣
a protective cover each with an open bottom,
挡风幌子各一件
and a pair of leather shoes.
开口烂底 皮头子一双
Two silver dollars.
大洋两块
No, it won't work!
不行 这不行
Mr. Dazhao, you can't use this.
大钊先生 这个您用得上
You can't! You can't!
真不行 真不行
And this.
还有这个
Worn out, wrong time,
破旧磨损 计时不准
one old pocket watch.
老怀表一只
Four silver dollars in total when sold.
总共四块大洋 当不当
Sold.
当了
I don't regret doing this.
不悔入当
Short sleeves with missing lapels, few buttons and no buttons,
缺襟短袖 少纽无扣
a protective cover each with an open bottom,
挡风悦子各一件
and a pair of leather shoes.
开口烂底 皮头子一双
Worn out, wrong time,
破旧磨损 计时不准
one old pocket watch.
老怀表一只
I don't regret doing this.
不悔入当
Shugui, come with me somewhere.
树贵 跟我去个地方
[Editorial board of the "Morning Bell"]
[《晨钟报》编辑部]
Come on, come on. Higher.
来来来 再高点
Higher, higher. Balance on both sides.
高了高了 两面平衡
Wait for me here.
你们在这儿等我一下
Good. Nailed it.
好 钉吧
Lao Xie.
老谢
Mr. Shou Chang! Welcome, welcome.
守常先生 欢迎欢迎啊
Just about to go to the station.
正准备去车站
No more pleasantries for now.
客套话先不多说了
Lend me thirty dollars quickly.
赶快借我三十块钱
I have a friend who has a family emergency.
我有个朋友家里头有点急事
You lend it to me
你借给我
and just take it out of my salary next month.
下个月从我的薪水里头扣就好了
OK.
好
Xiang Li!
襄理啊
Go and get thirty silver dollars.
去支三十块大洋来
Alright, alright.
好好好
Hurry up.
赶紧的
How's your health?
身体怎么样
Same as always, OK.
老样子 还好
You caught me off guard.
你搞得我措手不及
You see, the welcome ceremony is being set up for you.
你看 这欢迎仪式正给你布置呢
Good.
好
Here.
给
Shugui.
树贵
Thirty dollars.
三十块钱
Brother Ge.
葛大哥
As you said, poor people don't have a fragile life.
你说的 穷人不是脆着的命
Save a life, quickly!
救人要紧 快
Lao Xie.
老谢
You'll also have to lend me ten dollars.
你还得借给我十块钱
I need to get my stuff
我得把我东西
back from the pawnshop.
从当铺里头姨回来
Hurry up, hurry up and get it.
赶紧 赶紧的 赶紧去取
Good trip. How are you?
一路辛苦 你好你好
Come on, big guy.
来来来 大家伙
We warmly welcome
我们热烈欢迎
editor-in-chief Li Dazhao, who has returned from Japan.
从日本归来的李大钊主编
Good!
好
Hello.
你好
Student, take a look and see!
同学们看一看 瞧一瞧了
[Aurora College, Shanghai]
[上海震旦学院]
This issue of the "New Youth"
这一期的 《新青年》
especially "Youth" by Mr. Li Dazhao
尤其是李大钊先生写的 《青春》
is the most exciting.
最为精彩
Let me read you a paragraph:
我给大家伙念一段
"To advance civilisation for the world,"
为世界进文明
"to create happiness for mankind,"
为人类造幸福
"with our youthful selves,"
以青春之我
"to create a youthful family,"
创建青春之家庭
"a youthful nation,"
青春之国家
"a youthful people,"
青春之民族
"a youthful humanity,"
青春之人类
"a youthful earth,"
青春之地球
"a youthful universe..."
青春之宇宙
Sorry about that!
不好意思啊
Who's there?
谁呀
Did you see if there's anyone up here?
看下面有人了吗
It's her!
是她
The one with the accordion at the back!
背手风琴那个
That's me.
叫我
Did you see anyone down here?
看见下面有人了吗
What's going on?
怎么了
It's wet. The magazines are wet.
湿了 杂志也湿了
I was in a hurry to get to class and didn't see them.
我刚刚着急上课没看见
How about this,
要不然这样吧
I'll give you ten dollars.
我给你十块钱
You catch!
你接着啊
What an attitude!
什么态度啊
Who are you shouting at?
冲谁嚷嚷呢
What's wrong with me yelling at you?
我冲你嚷嚷怎么了
Get down here!
下来
Then you wait there.
那你在那儿给我等着
God there are people like this.
天哪还有这种人
Brother, I'm all wet.
哥 全湿了
Who are you shouting at?
你冲谁嚷嚷呢
Do you know what you've done wrong?
你知道自己做错了吗
Whoever you are, you've drenched the magazine
人 杂志全都让你给浇湿了
and you haven't even said you're sorry.
你连一句对不起都没说
I've given you the money.
我钱已经给你了
I've just made it very clear.
刚刚我说得很清楚啊
I was in a hurry to get to class, I didn't see it.
我着急上课我没看见
I was just up there, I couldn't get down.
我刚刚在上面我不方便下来
What more do you want from me?
你还想让我怎么样
Do you give money like that?
有你这么给钱的吗
I don't mean your money.
我不是说你钱
It's as much as it should be.
该多少钱就是多少钱
Qiaonian, how many copies?
乔年 数多少本
What's your attitude?
你什么态度啊
With a woman like you scattering flowers in the sky
有你这种天女散花一样
and throwing money away?
往下扔钱的吗
Thirteen copies.
十三本
Twenty-two cents per copy.
每本两毛二 一共是
How much money?
多少钱
Two dollars and eighty-six cents.
两块八毛六
Add to that the word "Sorry".
再加上一句话 对不起
I've given you ten dollars.
十块钱我已经给你了
You can pay for all your magazines for ten dollars.
十块钱能买你所有的杂志
Ten dollars will get you both a lot of food.
十块钱能让你们俩吃很多顿饭
Who wants to go out for dinner on your dime?
谁要拿你钱出去吃饭啊
Do you have any manners
你这人有没有礼貌
and are you reasonable?
讲不讲道理啊
Did your family ever teach you
你家里人有没有教过你
the rules?
什么是规矩啊
Rules, huh?
讲规矩是吧
Then I'll give you a good lecture on the rules today.
那我今天就好好给你讲讲规矩
This is a school.
这里是学校
You have broken a school rule.
你已经违反了校规
The school rule is
学校的规矩就是
that no one is allowed to set up a stall here.
谁都不能在这儿摆挺位
You've set up a stall and you're in breach of school rules.
你已经摆了摊位你就违反校规了
I'm still really surprised.
我还真是很奇怪呢
Who are you?
你们是谁啊
What are you doing?
干什么的
I suddenly remembered that I hadn't met you guys before.
我突然想起我没见过你们财
Sister, how did you get here?
姐 你们怎么过来的啊
Sister, we are new students.
姐姐 我们是新生
New students, are you?
新生是吗
New students are expected to follow the school rules.
新生那就更应该遵守学校校规了
The new students don't study hard,
新生不好好学习
they just set up shop and do business here
光知道在这儿摆位 做生意
which will delay their studies.
将来耽误了学业
How can you live up to the parents who provide for you?
你怎么对得起供养你们的父母
Who doesn't study well anymore?
谁不好好学习了
We call this work-study after school.
我们在课余时间这叫勤工俭学
French class is a preparatory class for work-study in France.
法语班是留法勤工俭学的预科班
Then we can work-study in France
那去法国能勤工俭学
but not in our own country.
在自己国家不能勤工俭学
What's the point?
什么道理啊
Work-study?
勤工俭学
That's a trendy way of putting it.
说得很潮流嘛
There are rules everywhere in China.
中国那么大哪里都有规矩
School rules are school rules.
学校就得讲学校的规矩
Yes, we are new students
是 我们是新生
and we don't know the rules.
校规我们不知道
But now that we know
但是现在我们知道了
we can walk
我们可以走
but before that happens, you have to say one word to us.
在这之前 你要跟我们说三个字
"Sorry"
对不起
We'll leave as soon as we've finished.
说完之后我们立马走人
I've grown up
我长这么大
and never said that word.
从来没有说过这三个字
Are you leaving?
你走不走
I'm not leaving.
我不走
OK.
好
Supervisor!
校监
Sister, don't!
姐姐 你别
Don't stop her. Let her shout.
别拦着 让她喊
Sister, don't shout.
姐姐 你先别喊
Shout!
喊啊
Supervisor!
校监
Sister, don't shout.
姐姐 你先别喊
We are not like the others.
我们跟别人不一样
The "New Youth" magazine is an emancipator of the mind!
《新青年》 杂志能让人解放思想
[Chen Qiaonian, second son of Chen Duxiu]
[陈乔年 陈独秀次子]
Do you know Mr. Li Dazhao?
你知道李大钊先生吗
I don't know Li Dazhao.
我不知道李大钊
You leaving?
走不走
Not leaving.
不走
OK, hold this for me.
好 帮我拿一下
Don't do this.
别这样
Not leaving, are you?
不走是吧
I'll do it.
我来
Sister!
姐姐
What are you doing? You want to go insane?
你干吗呢 要流氓啊
I didn't ask for trouble.
我可没要流误啊
The students are watching
同学们都看着呢
while I reasoned with her.
我跟她讲道理
I'm not being a jerk.
我没耍流氓
Put the magazines down.
把杂志放下
You're a stubborn person.
你这人怎么油盐不进啊
There's no reasoning with you!
跟你没道理可讲
Why do you have no sense at all?
怎么一点素质都没有啊
Sister, don't take our things!
姐姐 你别拿我们东西啊
Have a good talk!
有话好好说
You give me back the magazine!
你把杂志还给我
Sister!
姐姐
Make way!
让一下
Brother, let's sell it somewhere else.
哥 咱去别的地儿卖吧
Don't sell it here.
别在这儿卖了
Alright.
也行
Sell it there and nowhere else.
在那儿卖 哪儿都不去
Here you go.
给你
Thank you.
谢谢啊
Grandpa,
大爷
I'll set up a stall here
我在这儿摆个摊
to sell "New Youth" magazines.
卖《新青年》 杂志
What?
啥
I want a stall here selling magazines,
我在这儿摆个摊卖杂志
is it a concern for you?
得您的事吗
Selling books.
卖书啊
What book?
啥书啊
"New Youth"
《新青年》
Sell it, sell it.
卖吧卖吧
Thank you!
好勒 谢谢您
To love or not to love.
爱要不要
It's not easy to watch them.
看他们 其实也挺不容易的
They are the ones who work and study.
就是 他们勤工俭学呢
Let's all disperse and get on with it.
都散了吧 该干吗干吧
Close the door.
关门
Take a look and see!
看一看 瞧一瞧
Don't miss it passing by!
走过路过别错过
"New Youth", just published!
刚出版的 《新青年》
See Mr. Li Dazhao's "Youth"!
看李大钊先生的 《青春》
See the newly published "New Youth"!
看新出版的 《新青年》
Young man, how much is the magazine?
小伙子 书怎么卖的
Hello, twenty-two cents a copy.
你好 两毛二一本
Come and have a look.
来 您看看
I'll take a look.
我看看
Yes, I'll take one.
好 我来一本
Twenty-two cents.
两毛二
That's it. Thank you.
刚好 谢谢您啊
Have a good read. Qianian, receipt!
好书 乔年 入账
OK.
好
"New Youth"!
《新青年》
Hello.
您好
How much is "New Youth"?
《新青年》 怎么卖啊
Twenty-two cents a copy.
两毛二一本
I'll take one.
来一本
Take a look.
您看
That's it. Thank you.
刚好啊 谢谢
Hello, have a look at the "New Youth".
您好 看一下 《新青年》
Qiaonian!
乔年
Two copies!
两本了啊
Come, take a look!
来 您看
See Mr. Li Dazhao's "Youth"!
看李大钊先生的 《青春》
See the newly published "New Youth"!
看新出版的 《新青年》
Thank you!
谢谢啊
Brother, I've got one here too.
哥 我这儿也有一笔了
Don't mess it up.
赶紧记啊 别乱了
"New Youth"!
《新青年》
See Mr. Li Dazhao's "Youth"!
看季大钊先生的 《青春》
This is a well written paragraph.
这段写得好
Stop, stop, stop.
停一下 停一下 停一下
See Mr. Li Dazhao's "Youth"!
看李大钊先生的 《青春》
See the newly published "New Youth"!
看新出版的 《新青年》
Young man.
小伙计
Let me ask you something.
我跟你打听
Do you have
你这里有那个
the newly reissued issue
新复刊出版的
of the magazine that published
刊登了那个李大钊《青春》的
Li Dazhao's "Youth"?
那期杂志吗
Sure thing.
有有有
Let me have a look.
拿来我看看
Go ahead.
您看看
Many people like it. They're buying the magazine
好多人都特别喜它
just for that article.
专程来买呢
Yes. That's the one.
对 就是它
The Master had me looking for it for several days.
老爷让我找好几天了
Finally found it.
总算找到了
I'll buy two issues.
来 我买两本
Two?
两本啊
How much?
多少钱
Here you go.
来 给您
Forty-four cents all together.
一共是四毛四
Twenty-two cents each.
一本两毛二
Alright.
好好好
This one is new. Take it.
这本是新的 您拿好
Here.
来
No problem. It's ok if you don't buy it.
没事儿 不买也没事儿
You can read it first.
你们可以先看一下
You can't stop here. Move along.
不能停在这儿 快走
Right away.
马上走 马上走
Mister, we have to go.
老先生 走了
Coming!
来了来了来了
Here's your change.
来 给您找的钱
Here.
来来来
Thank you!
谢谢啊
Take care.
慢走
Alrighty.
好嘞
Alright, here you go.
好嘞 您拿好
Qiaonian,
乔年
are you keeping track?
你都记清了吗
That's another two issues.
这刚才又有两本啊
Yes.
好
I've got a few too.
我这边也有好几本
[Baishun Lane, Qianmenwei Street, Beijing]
[北京前门外大街百顺胡同]
Brothers,
哥几个
Let's not go to second-rate tea rooms.
咱们不去二流的茶室
And let's not go to third-rate lodgings.
也不去三流的下处
But rather to this first-rate sing-song house!
就到这一等的清吟小班
Lan Xiang Ban!
兰香班
Gui Jin Luan!
桂金鸾
Young Masters, be quiet.
各位爷 别叫
Your brother is here!
哥哥我来了
Young Masters.
各位爷
Master Zhang, to tell you the truth,
张公子 不瞒您说
right now, Gui Jin Luan
桂金鸾 这会儿啊
is entertaining Master Hu from your Peking University.
正在同候你们北大的胡老爷呢
The music is coming from her room.
您听 这琴声就是她屋里的
Master Hu?
胡老爷
Which Master Hu?
哪个胡老爷
The Master Hu from Peking University, Hu Jun.
就是你们北大的胡均胡老爷
That's right.
对
He's been here for several days.
他都在这儿待了好几天了
Hu Jun?
胡均哪
I know him!
我认识
He got a professorship due to his relative Duan Qirui.
仗着是段祺瑞的亲戚混了个教授
Taking money and not teaching properly.
拿着钱不好好给人上课
Spending all day eating, drinking, and gambling,
整天就知道吃喝蝶赌
his reputation stinks to high heaven.
那名声 臭了去了都
Since he's been here for a few days,
既然都来好几天了
then ask him to take a break.
那就请他歇歇吧
Let's give him a hand.
我们替他出点力
Besides, as a teacher,
再说了 这当老师的
he ought to defer to students.
也得让着点学生
Get out of the way.
闪开
Master Zhang, Master Zhang!
张公子 张公子
What are you doing just standing there?
还愣着干什么呀
Hurry up and call the police!
还不赶紧去报警
Master Zhang!
张公子
Stop fighting!
别打了
Help!
来人哪
[Shanghai]
[上海]
There's a purse here.
哥 这儿有个包
Where did you find it?
哪儿捡的
Inside the book.
书缝里面
Do you have any recollection
那你有没有印象
of anyone who was here with that purse?
谁来的时候拿这皮包
Can't remember.
记不清了
Five hundred and eighty-three silver dollars.
五百八十三块大洋
So much money.
这么多钱
Five eighty-three!
五百八十三
Quiet!
小点声
Let me count it.
我数数
Song Ah Di.
宋阿弟
There's no address. Only a name.
这也没写地址 光有个人名啊
If no one claims it, then we've hit the jackpot.
要是没人来找咱就发财了呀
Hit what jackpot?
发什么财呀
If you had lost this money, wouldn't you be worried?
这钱要是你丢的你着不着急
Then how do we give it back?
那怎么还给人家
Let's wait.
等等吧
See if anyone comes to claim it.
看看有没有人来取
Clean up.
收拾东西
Not going home?
不回家呀
We'll be going right away.
马上就回了
It's getting dark.
天都黑了
Should get going.
早点回去吧
Take care.
您慢走啊
See you tomorrow.
明天见
Friends, friends.
朋友 朋友
Have a drink. No, no.
一起喝点吧 不不
Why not?
为什么 不不
Just sit there, then.
在这里坐着吧
Brother.
哥
Hungry.
饿
Bear with it.
忍着
What if I'm still hungry?
忍着也饿怎么办
Are you hungry?
你饿吗
I...
我
I'm also hungry.
也饿
Then how do you bear your hunger?
那你饿你怎么忍
With all my might.
使劲忍
Little mister.
小先生 小先生
Aren't you the uncle who bought that magazine.
您不是买杂志那个伯伯吗
Yes, yes.
是啊 是啊
Little misters, have you seen my purse?
小先生 你们见到我的皮包了吗
First of all, calm down.
您先别着急
What does your purse look like?
您那皮包长什么样啊
It's brown.
棕色的
And filled with the Master's silver certificates.
里面装的全是东家的银票啊
You can stop looking.
您别找了
Is this your purse?
这是您的包吗
That's exactly it.
就是这个 就是这个
I can't just give it to you.
不 不能现在给您
I have to ask you a few questions.
我得问您几个问题
Sure, as you should.
好 应该的
Go ahead and ask.
你问 你问
What do you have
您的这个皮包里面
inside this purse?
装了些什么东西
Six silver certificates.
六张银票
Five hundred and eighty-three silver dollars all together.
一共五百八十三块大洋
It's a divident from the soap factory.
是肥皂厂给东家的红利
Only silver certificates?
只有银票吧
Are there any silver coins?
有没有什么现大洋
Only certificates, no coins.
只有银票 没有现大洋
Is there anything else besides that?
那除了这个之外还有没有别的
There is also a bill
还有一个账单
with my name on it.
上面有我的名字
My name is Song Ah Di.
我 我叫宋阿弟
What you've said all matches up. You can count it.
您说的这些都对上了 您点点
It's all here.
都在 都在
Thank heavens.
谢天谢地
My master's money has finally been found.
东家的钱总算找回来了
Thank you both.
谢谢二位
Mister,
先生 先生
you don't need to be like this.
您别这样 您别这样
Thank you both young gentlemen.
谢谢两位小先生
You've really saved this old man's life.
你们真是救了老朽的一条命啊
I had thought that
我本来想啊
if I couldn't find this money
这钱要是找不回来
I'd have to jump in the Huangpu river.
我就去跳黄浦江了
Don't be like this.
您别这样
It's good enough that you got it back.
东西找回来就好了
You're welcome.
您千万别客气
Why don't you put it away,
您把它收好了
and get back home quickly.
赶紧回家去吧
Young gentlemen,
二位小先生
please go with me to see my master.
请跟我一起去见见我们东家
He will definitely reward you.
他一定有重赏
No, no.
别别别
It's nothing. There's no need for a reward.
举手之劳 重赏就不必了
You should go back home.
您赶快回家去吧
We have to go back to the school.
我们俩也得回学校了
But, but.
这 这
Young gentlemen,
二位小先生
let's see this to the end.
救人救到底
Look, it's already dark.
你看 天这么晚了
It's not safe for an old man
老朽一个人带着这么多银票
to be carrying so much money.
也不安全
Would you two please escort me home?
烦请二位把我送到家吧
Brother, let's see the uncle home.
哥 咱送伯伯回家吧
Let's go.
走
Don't worry. Let me give you a hand.
没事 我来帮你
This way.
就在前边
Young gentlemen, you really are good people.
小先生 你们可真是好人哪
[Lu Wanliu residence, Shanghai]
[上海卢湾柳宅]
This way, gentlemen.
来 二位小先生 来
We're almost there.
到了 这就到了啊
Uncle Song.
宋伯
Let us help.
我们来帮忙吧
No need.
不用不用
Uncle Song.
宋伯
You've got your own work.
你们忙你们的 你们忙你们的
Here.
来来来
We're here.
来 到了啊
Please come in.
来 请进请进请进
Here, young gentlemen.
来 二位小先生
Please.
请请请
Right this way.
来 请进 请进
Uncle, now that the money has been safely delivered,
伯伯 钱既然已经安全地送到了
we should be on our way.
那我们就先回去了
Not at all.
别别别
Now that you're already here,
既然已经来了
I would like to ask you two to help me testify.
务请二位小先生替我做个证明
Without you present, I can't explain it properly.
你们不在 我说不清楚的
Master will say I'm lying.
老爷会说我说谎的
Alright.
行
Here, put it down.
来来来 放下放下
You put it down too.
你也放下 你也放下
Here, take a seat.
来 请坐请坐
A seat here. Alright.
请坐 好
Bring out the coffee.
上咖啡
Young gentlemen, please wait.
二位小先生 请稍候
I will find the Master.
我去请老爷
Please, sit.
来 坐
Master!
老爷
Please, the coffee.
请用咖啡
Thank you.
谢谢
I'm hungry.
俄
Bear it.
忍着
I know.
我知道
Why are you two here?
怎么是你们啊
Why are you here?
怎么是你
What do you mean, why?
还怎么是我呢
This is my home.
这是我家
What are you two doing here?
你们两个来干什么
This is your home?
这是你家
Mother, these are the two scoundrels from today
妈 这就是我今天跟你说的
I was telling you about.
那两个无赖
Who's the scoundrel?
谁是无赖呀
Can't you tell the truth for once?
你能不能说点真话呀
Who spilled the water all over us today?
谁今天把水洒了我们一身啊
I did spill the water. Didn't I give you money?
水是我洒的 钱我给你们了
Is that the way to give us money?
有你那么给钱的吗
Then how should I have done it?
那我应该怎么给啊
Fellow student, you have still not understood
同学 你现在都没有明白
how you are wrong, have you?
你自己错在哪儿是吗
Who has wronged whom?
谁对谁错啊
Setting up stalls without permission is in violation of school rules.
你们乱摆地摊已经违反了校规
You've brought your wares here.
家伙什儿带来了
Were you going to set up a street stall in my home?
怎么着 在我家要摆地摊啊
Set it up then.
摆啊 铺啊
Child, don't speak this way.
囡囡 你不要这样讲话
This way, Master.
这边老爷
Master, these are the two young gentlemen.
老爷 就是这二位小先生
This is our Master.
这是我们家老爷
How do you do?
您好
How should address the two of you?
二位年轻人怎么称呼
I am Chen Qiaonian.
我是陈乔年
Chen Yannian.
陈延年
Thank you both.
谢谢你们
Thank you. You're welcome.
谢谢 您别客气
Dad, why are you thanking them?
爸 谢他们干吗呀
These are the two
就这两个人
who were arguing with me at school.
今天中午在学校跟我大吵一架
They were setting up a stall to sell things.
他们两个人摆地摊做生意
I kicked them out.
我把他们轰出去了
Sister, didn't we already explain to you
姐姐 我们不是给你解释过了吗
that our stall is a work-study program.
我们摆地是为了勤工俭学
You've already violated the school rules.
你们已经违反校规了
What work can you do? What student can you be?
勤什么工啊 俭什么学啊
Liu Mei!
柳眉
These are our guests!
人家是客人
How can you speak to guests in such a way?
你跟客人怎么能这么说话呢
How rude!
没礼貌
Please have a seat.
二位 请坐 请坐
Alright.
好啦
Sit, sit!
坐 坐 坐
Old Song has told me everything.
老宋刚才都告诉我了
The two of you, by not pocketing the money,
你们两个拾金不味
have really helped our family.
是我们柳家的恩人
I must thank you properly.
我要好好地感谢你们
Old Song.
老宋
Master.
老爷
This small gift is a token of my regard.
这点薄礼是我的一点心意
Please take it.
你们收下
We can't take the money.
这钱我们不能要
We did what we ought to do.
那是我们应该做的事情
If we really wanted money,
如果我们真想要钱的话
couldn't we have gotten more with the five hundred?
那五百多不是更多吗
Now that the money has been safely returned,
钱既然已经安全地拿回来了
we are going to go now.
那我们就先走了
Uncle, we will take our leave.
伯伯 我们先走了
Wait, don't go.
别呀 别 这
The both of you,
二位 二位
stay, stay.
留步 留步
I've heard you say
我听你们说
that you are doing a work-study program.
你们现在在勤工俭学
Then you must have some financial difficulties.
想必经济上一定有困难
If you insist on refusing this money,
如果这个钱你们执意不要的话
why don't we do this. I am the administrator at the school.
这样吧 我是这个学校的校董
I can waive all of your
我可以把你们在这个学校的
tuition and miscellaneous fees.
学费和杂费全部免掉
It's a matter of course to pay for tuition if attending school.
上学交学费那是天经地义的事情
We pay what should be paid.
该多少钱就是多少钱
We'll figure it out ourselves.
这个我们自己会想办法的
Thank you for your kindness.
谢谢您的好意
We will take our leave.
我们先告辞了
Wen Yao!
文耀
Wen Yao, is there anything to eat?
文耀 有吃的没有啊
I'm starving.
快把我饿死了
Yannian, Qiaonian?
延年 养年
Uncle Wu?
吴伯伯
What are you doing here?
你们怎么在这儿啊
Old Wu, do you know these two?
吴老 你跟他们俩认识
Far more than know!
何止认识
These two are Chen Duxiu's sons.
这不是陈独秀那俩小子吗
Chen Yannian. Chen Qiaonian.
陈延年 陈乔年
So they are Chen Duxiu's young masters!
原来他们是陈独秀的公子啊
No wonder.
怪不得 怪不得
Uncle,
伯伯
he is his own person, and we are us.
他是他 我们是我们
We don't have anything to do with him.
我们跟他没有任何的关系
We're going back to school now.
我们先回学校了
Any later and the school gate will be closed.
再不回去学校校门就该关了
Farewell.
告辞了
Yes, alright.
好 好
Take care, young gentlemen.
二位小先生 慢走慢走
What? Just leaving like this?
怎么 这就走了
But, these two guys...
不是 这俩小子
How did they end up here with you?
怎么到你这儿来了
Elder Wu, have a seat.
吴老 坐 坐
Alright, alright.
好 好 好
Get the cooks started on a meal.
让厨房做饭
[Daheituo Village, Laoting, Hebei]
[河北乐亭大黑坨村]
[Li Baohua, son of Li Dazhao]
[李葆华 李大钊之子]
[Li Xinghua, daughter of Li Dazhao]
[李星华 李大钊之女]
Xinghua.
星华
Who are you?
你谁呀
You're acting like a real man now.
现在像个男子汉样了啊
Mom!
娘娘娘
What is it?
唯了
The weasels came again?
这黄鼠狼又来了
Grab a stick to drive them away!
你拿个棍子赶着点
Don't let them bite your younger sister again!
别又咬着你妹妹
It's not weasels!
不是黄鼠狼
It's not weasels, then what is it?
[1057]
A silly lump.
憨坨呗
[Zhao Renlan, wife of Li Dazhao]
回来了
I thought you would only be able to come back at night.
我想着晚上才能到呢
When I look at it, there is nothing wrong.
我一看也没什么事
I changed my to ticket to an early morning one.
我就把票改成早晨的了
Rented a donkey cart. Getting on there's also no people.
霍了辆驴车 道上也没人
In no time, I was pulled to our house entrance.
一下就拉到咱们家门口
Fast.
快
The fire... firewood pile.
那柴柴火
Those siberian weasels have been coming to the firewood pile.
那个黄鼠狼老来柴火坏
Xinghua, Xinghua's been bitten by them.
星华 星华都被胶了
Her, her brother grabs a stick
她她哥就老拿着棍子
driving away and hurrying over there
跟那儿赶着打呢
to find weasels
找黄鼠狼
Hurry, come here!
快来呀
This is your guys' dad!
这是你们的
Don't you guys shout to want to find your dad all the time?
你们不是成天喊着要找吗
Hurry over, call for "dad".
快来喊多阳
Dad's back.
参来了
Dad's come back. Quickly.
快
Xinghua.
星华
You...
你
Want you dad, want your dad. Go search.
要多要多找
Dad's come, and you...
来了你就
You stay in your den.
你就处窝子
You quickly!
你快点
Stop being stubborn there.
别跟那儿促
You, quickly go.
你快去啊
Li Baohua
李葆华
Are you still wetting your bed right now?
你现在还尿烧吗
Xinghua, Xinghua, Xinghua!
星华星华星华
Enough now, enough now.
行了行了
Come down, come down.
下来吧 下来吧
Don't let your dad hold you.
别让多抱着了
Dad's tired. Quickly.
多累了快
Wash your face, wash your face.
洗把脸 洗把脸
Dad's washing his face, is that okay?
洗把脸 行不行
Dad's going to wash his hands.
洗个手
Then I'll hold you again, is that okay?
会再抱星华行不行
Good.
好
Xinghua, catch a big chaffinch.
星华抓大花鸡
Slaughter chicken!
杀鸡
Tonight we're eating chicken!
咱今晚吃鸡
Our... our family can finally eat a reunion meal.
吃上团圆饭了
Student Li Baohua.
李葆华同学
Come out and catch chicken.
出来抓鸡啊
Stop it over there!
那边截住
Let me help, miss.
我帮忙吧姐
No problem.
没事
Dad, what is this?
这是什么
This is called Junqi (land battle chess).
这个叫军模
Dad, why didn't buy me something good to eat?
你怎么不给我买点好吃的呢
Didn't you eat all the big reed flowers, you still want to eat something good?
大芦花都吃了 还吃好吃的
How much good food are you able to eat?
好吃的才能吃几顿
But this land battle chess, we can play with it for a long time.
但是这个军棋我们能玩好久呢
Do you guys know?
你们知道吗
When dad was in Japan,
在日本的时候
everyone relied on this to relieve boredom.
全靠这个来解阀
Baohua, don't think that this land battle chess doesn't look good.
葆华你别看这个军棋不好看
This is what dad personally made for you.
这可是多亲手给你做的
Dad will teach you, okay?
好
This Junqi
这个军棋啊
needs to have two people to battle.
得两个人对阵
What's a victory?
怎么叫赢啊
I take this piece,
我拿这个军棋
occupy your military command center.
占领了你的司令部
This is a victory.
这个就叫赢了
You see these pieces on the chessboard,
然后你看棋盘上的这些棋子
The biggest piece within these pieces is this one.
这些棋子里边最大的是这个
General.
大将
The last one is this one, landmine.
最后是这个地雷
Landmine, excluding the military engineer,
地雷除了工兵之外
is afraid of no one.
谁都不怕
Xinghua.
星华
It's burning hot.
烫啊
Do you understand?
听明白了吧
Understand.
明白了
Come.
来
I'll teach you how to move.
我教你怎么走啊
Dad, drink water.
喝水
Thank you, Xinghua!
谢谢星华
Dad, what is the biggest move?
哪个是最大的来着
Just now, didn't dad tell you?
刚才多不是告诉你了吗
General.
大将
Dad. Then when can you become the biggest official?
那你什么时候能当最天的管
Like this, then we can eat meat every day.
这样咱们就可以天天吃肉了
Who said dad wanted to be an official?
谁说参要当官啊
Didn't the village people all say？
村里人不都说吗
Studying is so you can become a big official.
读书就是为了当大官
Dad, aren't you this village's
你不是咱们村里
person who reads the most.
读书最多的人吗
For sure, you can be the biggest official.
肯定能当个最大的官
Dad, after you become a big official,
多当上大官之后
won't we have money then.
是不是就有钱了呀
When the time comes, can you buy me fruit candy to eat.
到时候可以给我买水果糖吃吗
Second girl let me have a lick,
二妞给我器过一口
it was especially good.
特别好吃
Come.
来
Saying it like this,
那这么说
you guys all want dad to become an official.
你们都想让参当官啊
Being an official is incredible!
当官厉害啊
And there's money!
还有钱
Is being an official is incredible?
当官厉害吗
Baohua, just now dad taught you land battle chess.
葆华刚才参教你这军棋
Who do you think is the most incredible in here?
你觉得这里边谁最厉害
General.
大将啊
Not right.
不对
General is afraid of the landmine.
大将怕地雷
Right.
对
Then, the landmine is the most incredible.
那就地雷最厉害
Then who is the landmine afraid of?
那地雷怕谁啊
The landmine is afraid of the military engineer.
地雷怕工兵
Oh right!
对
Then military engineer is the most incredible.
那就工兵最厉害
That's not right.
不对啊
After the military engineer removes the landmine,
工兵除完地雷以后
it will die with whoever it meets!
碰谁都得死啊
What you said is correct.
你说得对
The military engineer acting alone
工宾作为一个人
is surely the weakest.
确实是最弱的
But the military engineer
但是工兵呢
can make a lot of incredible weapons.
可以做很多很多厉害的武器
You guys think about it.
你们想啊
A pile of military engineers stacked together
一堆工兵凌到一块
can create many, many different kinds
能做出各种各样
of weapons in one piece.
很多很多的武器
Then officials, aren't they afraid of them?
那当官的是不是怕他们
So although second girl's father is a small town official
所以二妞虽然是镇上的官
but her when her mom and grandmother
但是二妞娘和菇
grabs a broom, he will run.
一抄扫最他就跑了
Therefore, later dad will become a military engineer.
所以呀 以后可是要当工兵的
Xinghua, Baohua.
星华葆华
After you guys grow up
以后你们长大之后呢
No matter if you become a military engineer or something else.
无论是当工兵还是当其他的
It is up to you to decide.
这个由你们自己选择
But remember,
但是记住
no matter what we become,
无论我们当什么
we need to be a strong and disciplined person.
我们要当一个堂堂正正的人
We need to be
我们要当 一个
a person who never harms ordinary people.
永远不福害老百姓的人
This is a present Dad gives to you.
这是参送给你们的礼物
Thank you, Dad!
谢谢多
What thank you? Take a look.
谢什么看看
Such a beautiful case.
好漂亮的盒子呀
Case is very beautiful
盒子好漂亮
Recently, a friend
姐 前段时间 一个朋友
made me go to Nanjing to be an official.
让我去南京当官
It is said that it's a lucrative job.
据说是个肥差
Income is also pretty high.
收入也挺高的
But I declined it.
但是我拒绝了
I said the warlords right now
你说现在的军阀
cause damage to the country and suffering to the people,
福国映民
having the ordinary people deal with their days so bitterly.
把老百姓的日子弄得那么苦
When I was returning back from Japan,
我从日本回国的时候
I made a malicious oath.
我就立下毒誓了
Even if I die,
我就是死
I will never follow their bad example.
我也绝不跟他们同流合污
You won't blame me right?
你不会怪我吧
I listen to you.
我听你的
I know you won't do things that will cause harm to the ordinary people.
我知道你不会去做褐害老百姓的事
We can't let other people stab us in the back, right?
咱不能让人家截咱脊梁骨哪 是吧
Do what you want to do.
你想做什么就去做什么
Us three mother and children you... You don't need to worry.
我们娘仁你 你不用担心
In the countryside, we can get through anything.
在乡下怎么都能过
Then... when you become an official,
那你不当官了
what plans do you have?
有啥打算呢
I plan to go back to Beijing and continue running my magazine.
我打算回北京继续办我的杂志
Although, I say it doesn't earn as much as an official,
虽然说挣的没有当官的多
But in any case, our food and clothing, we don't need to worry about.
但是好友 咱们吃穿不愁
Moreover, that is what I have always wanted to do.
而且那也是我一直想做的事
You go steadily do it.
你踏实去办
I'll keep watch of this house.
我守着这个家
It's just that this work
就是我这个事吧
may have dangers.
可能会有危险
Running a magazine, isn't it just dealing with some cultural things?
办杂志 不就是弄一些文化的事
How can there still be danger?
唯还会有危险呢
You know my ambitions...
你知道我的志向
is for sure not only running a magazine.
肯定不光是办杂志
I know that you are a person who wants to do big things.
我知道你是干大事的人
Doing the right things.
干的是正事
You dealing with those cultural thing.
你说你弄的那些文化
I also can't make sense of what the meaning is.
我也搞不懂是啥意思
I am afraid that it will give you an impediment.
我就怕给你拖后腿
How can it?
怎么会呢
With you behind my back,
有你在我背后
I won't mention much steadiness.
我别提多踏实了
Beijing is cold in winter,
北京冬天冷 你又老写字
Take this hand stove
拿着这手炉啊
to warm up.
烫
I made a case for you
我就给你做了一个套子
Look.
你看
Tie it up this way, and it's nice and warm
这样扣上 又暖和
and you won't burn your hand.
又不烫手
It's suitable.
合适
I bang on the small gong.
我把小钢当当敲
Peking University is really nonsense.
北京大学真胡闹
Quarrelling from jealousy, hitting each other.
争风吃酷打相打
Forced to send Cai Yuanpei
只好派蔡元培
to take over Peking University Hall.
接管北京大学堂
The cultured sweep the floor.
斯文扫地呀
A great country's highest educational institute
泱泱大国 最高学府
has unexpectedly raised such a group of scum.
竞养着这么一群败类
This country, what hopes does it still have?
这个国家 还有什么希望
Right.
是啊
This group of students went as far as to quarrel from jealousy,
这帮学子竟然还争风吃酷
striking violently.
大打出手
What is this? Right!
这是什么呀 对
Exactly.
就是
I... come to you for advice.
我呢 是来向你请教的
Tell me, what do you think Li Yuanhong is doing?
你说黎元洪他抽什么风
He gave three gold medals
他连下三道金牌
to make me hurry to Beijing to take position as Peking University's headmaster.
让我赶到北京去任北大的校长
What is the reason?
所谓何因
This President Li Yuanhong
这黎元洪大总统啊
was unbearably mocked by Duan Qirui.
被段祺瑞挤对得够哈
[Wang Daxie, styled Bo Tang, diplomat of the Beiyang government]
[汪大燮 字 伯棠 北洋政府外交官员]
He wanted to do something practical to court favors
他想做点实事邀买人心
to compete with Duan Qirui.
和段祺瑞抗衡
Fighting doesn't work here, so his communication
这武的不行啊 他就来文的
coincided with a scandal at Peking University.
正赶上北大出丑闻
This President Li
这黎大总统啊
took the opportunity to remove Duan Qirui's trusted aide,
就超机撤了段祺瑞的亲信
Hu Renyuan's, position of headmaster.
胡仁源的校长职务
Your disciple Fan Yuanlin recommended you,
你的门生范源廉推荐了你
naturally to obtain popular support.
自然是众望所归了
I know.
我知道
The current Peking University,
现在的北大
we can say that it is already rotten to the core.
可以说已经是烂透
I just don't want to wade in these muddy waters.
我可不想壁这个浑水呀
Jiemin says one thing but means another.
子民言不由表吧
Your people are already all in Beijing.
你人都到北京了
Didn't you just indicate your attitude?
不正说明你的态度了吗
Brother Bo Tang, you know me well.
知我者伯棠兑也
Frankly saying.
坦率地说吧
Before going up north,
北上之前呢
I specially paid a visit to Mr. Sun Zhongshan.
我专门拜访了孙中山先生
Mr. Sun said to me that
孙先生与我一席之谈
he hopes that I can turn around Peking University's atmosphere
他希望我能把北大的校风扭转
and establish a top ranking school that can rise in the world.
创建能蹄身世界的一流学府
He also hopes that I
先生还希望我
cultivate the banner of China's modern education
树中国现代教育之旗帜
and hope that I can soon educate people for the country.
希望我能为国家早点培养栋梁之材
It's true. Education saves the nation, science saves the nation.
是啊 教育救国 科学救国
Talent saves the nation.
人才救国
This is exactly the ideal I, Cai Yuanpei, pursue.
这正是我蔡元培之追求的理想
Currently, China has many things waiting to be done.
当今中国百废待兴
Starting first with the atmosphere,
开风气之先的
nothing can surpass the rise of Chen Duxiu's
莫过于陈独秀所兴起的
New Culture Movement.
新文化运动
The most appealing
最有吸引力的
also can't surpass the high rise of Chen Duxiu's
也莫过于陈独秀所高擎的
banners of both democracy and science.
科学与民主两面大旗
Spreading democracy and science.
普及科学与民主
The root is in education.
根子在教育
You, Cai Yuanpei.
你蔡元培
If we can use the treasure of Peking University to reform and innovate
要是能借北大这块宝地改革创新
to revive our Chinese nation,
重振我中华民族
we will then have a support and hope.
就有了依托和希望
Brother Bo Tang's words
佰棠兄之所言
is exactly the aspiration of I, Cai Yuanpei.
正是蔡元培我之心志